The narck Reef is a geotextile bag reef
and its primary objective was Coastal
protection the road across nck was built
in 1921 by the main road it was the
Pacific Highway to Sydney but the
trouble is to miss the river they pushed
it out onto the June so it's always been
an area that's very narrow in
1999 my company won the tender for the
Northern Gold Coast Beach protection
strategy which had a number of elements
the primary one was nourishment and it
was really a repeat of what was done in
1974 we had the new control structure
which was built in ' 86 which was the
Gold Coast Seaway so what we wanted was
another control point just this side of
surface Paradise we looked at groins we
looked at beach dewatering you know
widening the dunes and the one that came
out best was a submerged artificial Reef
without the added bonuses of Surfing and
Diving it was clearly the best
solution why a reef a reef is a coastal
engineer dream in a way in that you can
reduce the wave energy without having to
stop all the wave energy and a reef does
that perf perfectly by Breaking the
Waves and dissipating the energy we've
constructed a structure that you can't
see but it's constantly reducing the
sand transport and the storm cut so we
have a wider Beach a more stable Beach
so the lifeguards can use the stability
inure of the reef to plant their Flags
in the best
Spot the Australian dredging industry
was developed on the Gold Coast McQuade
won the contract for dropping the
sandbags he had bought in a split Hull
Hopper barge that he developed
specifically for doing this type of work
he hired local go Coast boys who
understood the surf and they would
actually bring the dredge in between
sets and they would position it exactly
right where they'd have someone looking
behind them to check when the next wave
would be breaking over the stern it was
a lot of fun building that it was built
on tear so the boat would come in drop a
bag move out it then dread sand up into
the bag and it was filled on board and
then it come out and it was dropped out
the bottom it was just a endless job
keeping up with the number of bags and
then when it was finished we had to do
monitoring to see what was happening
both up the beach and down the beach and
to work it all in together the survivors
were very very
busy the difference between a geotextile
structure and a concrete or rock
structure is the type of growth we get a
very soft growth which is again safe for
surface but it's also better for diving
and better for the environment because
we get a a much more diverse habitat 10
m of water we're getting Kelps we're
getting Turtles and I've dive with
dolphins we took one of the top marine
biologists in Australia for a swim out
there one day and before he went in the
water he said it's just going to be
another Fisher tractor I can tell you
that now Angus when he came back he said
you've done it the geotextile is what
makes the difference
the data that's been collected over the
last 10 years from video cameras and
other measurements that have been taken
at n clearly show that it's been a
highly successful device or structure
for maintaining the health of the beach
in terms of the beach width and that's
been his primary objective